Welcome to À LA FRENCH.
In this episode,
we welcome our last
guest of the season.
And this guest is a pioneer.
He is the leader. He is the final boss.
The final boss of AI as we know it today.
He is creating today a
global platform.
He does World Models.
And this guest, we will discuss with
him for an hour and a half.
And exclusively in
À LA FRENCH, let's go!
Important announcement.
When we announced the
À LA FRENCH evening on June 12,
in less than 24 hours,
the 250 places were sold.
So we had a great
evening, but hundreds of
people couldn't come
and were on a waiting list.
And we don't like frustration.
So we decided to do it again, but bigger, for the À LA FRENCH conference.
On December 3, we'll see you there.
We will be 1200, coming
from all over France to celebrate
French tech and a certain vision of tech.
We are a nation of engineers.
We invented Minitel before
the Internet, the TGV before Hyperloops,
DivX, X264, VLC, before
streaming on Netflix.
We are not going to let anyone tell us
how we do tech, are we?
Come on, the conference that has a certain idea of technology, will be on December 3rd.
One day for the YouTube show community, announcement
preview, guest
rare, gifts, games.
And pay attention, this is going to be very French.
This is going to be the most incredible tech conference
to which you
have never attended.
And we will celebrate together
a certain idea of technology.
You can go to
alafrench.org right now,
reserve your seats with reduced rates for those who cannot afford it
and support rates for those who can.
So we will meet on December 3rd live.
And in the meantime, we're going back to the episode.
We are in À LA FRENCH
and you know the game.
To guess the guest, in 4 points,
if you know it immediately,
3 points if you need hints, 2
points if you need more hints,
and 1 point when everything has already been said.
Are you ready to play, Steve?
I'm ready.
Ready for what?
Me, I'm going to win.
Okay, let's go.
So, in 4 points.
Our guest is an
extremely well-known researcher.
No, we're joking.
It's Yann LeCun.
Okay, we won't waste any time.
Welcome, Yann.
It's a pleasure to be here.
Thank you for inviting me.
In addition, Neon Noir is
a place you know.
You come here from time to time, when you come to France.
Yes, 2-3 times, I've already been here.
It's changed a lot.
It's become populated, furnished, expanded.
You know with Yann
for longer than we do.
Since the very beginning of ZML.
We were introduced by Gabriel.
By Gabriel Synnaeve.
And then, for the story, we got into
it, got into it in the sense... "Heyyyy !"
We got into a fight.
We got into a fight about
programming languages.
Yes.
And in particular, what is called multi-stage programming.
So, referring to a language called Terra,
which was a kind of super set of Lua.
Yes.
So, the idea is to have
metaprogramming in the language.
You see, actually, you have only one control flow.
where you program the language
using the language itself.
In contrast to a macro, or a template, or all metaprogramming.
And so, he had told me... "ah!!"
And I see you too, Yann,
every time,
because whenever Steve makes
a very Frenchmaxing tweet,
with raclette or
things like that, in
Savoie, all of that, there's a
little like from Yann LeCun.
That's kind of it.
I can always count on it.
At first, I was happy.
I looked.
Now, I said yes.
Is that, the French Maxing?
Frenchmaxxing, it's nothing now.
It's a maximization of France.
Maximization.
As Victor Hugo said, who
used, I don't know what word,
then someone told him: "But
that's not a French word."
He said, "Well, now, if."
It's still cool to be called
Hugo when you can define what.
The dictionary, it's me.
But this discussion, the reason
for which we had discussed this,
is because I
am a big fan of LISP.
And LISP, it's a
language... Exactly.
Data is code.
Yes, data is code, and
then you can tinker.
It's a
programmable programming language.
There are a lot of parentheses
that we're going to use.
That's not a problem.
Me, I've never been able to get used to it.
Is that true?
I've done a lot of closures.
Were you an Emacs guy?
No, but in Emacs, I was a customer.
I wasn't a programmer at Emacs.
However, when I did a lot of Clojure, which I love,
in fact, pushed by someone
who is called Pierre-Yves Ritschard
who is the CTO
of Poolside, now.
I really felt like I was creating a language, you see, a language of the future.
Finally, somewhere in the past,
since syntax is all that matters.
It's a bit in the past.
But damn, I've never managed to get it right.
Parentheses, they make me... I did everything, the colorings, the gadgets and all that.
I've never managed to get it right.
And a little known fact,
in 87, when I finished my doctorate,
I met a young student from polytechnique called Léon Botou.
Oh!
And then, he said, I would like to do a
project for my final year at Polytechnique.
Will I
do an internship with you?
I told him, you can't, because
I haven't finished my thesis.
It's not a problem, I
won't tell the school.
And I told him, well,
listen, I'm starting to write
a new neural network simulator.
Do you want to help me?
And I said, I would really like
to have an interface language.
I thought about using
Forth and things like that.
Instead of inventing a language,
it might actually be a LISP.
So, I would really like a LISP interpreter.
And we both had Amiga 1000s.
I see that you don't have
one on your table here.
But that's a shame.
Yes, next time, that will be fixed.
But anyway, I didn't insult
you, I brought you a BeBox.
A BeBox.
But actually, the BeBox
is a copy of the Amiga.
Exactly.
There you go.
And you did it on purpose, of course.
So no, but we have a
conversation on Twitter, actually.
Yann had bounced back
and actually, he had explained.
Maybe it's a bit difficult to
find Amigas today, right?
Less than BeBoxes, I
can tell you. That one...
You can find emulators and all that.
But you can also buy them.
And Léon, in three weeks,
wrote a tablet-list
in C, which I used
as a front-end.
Then, I went to do my postdoc in Toronto.
And actually, we used that system, which
initially was called SN,
Simulateur Neuronal,
which later became Lush,
when we open-sourced it in 2002.
And I used it in all my research with my
students until 2011,
where then we switched to Torch.
In Lua, so.
So, it was based on Lua and then,
PyTorch, but that was much later.
So, there was a long lifespan.
There were successive versions.
What were we following?
It was written about backpropagation, multi-layer networks, etc.
justement, the backpropagation of the gradient, is a bit the foundation
of how today,
the learning engine
neural networks
is a bit based on that.
Already, back then, your thesis, it's about the
core of neural networks.
So, what is it?
Is it 87, the end of the thesis?
For the few Padawans who haven't
yet... Are you born?
Just, just, just.
But then, you go to Bell Labs, right?
No, first, I do a postdoc at the
University of Toronto with Jeff Hinton.
Ah yes, okay.
No, and after, I went
to Bell Labs, in late 88.
Okay, you stay there for 15
years, right, approximately?
So, 12 years at AT&T.
So, Bell Labs is the
research lab of AT&T.
It later changed its name because
AT&T split up, anyway,
but about a dozen years.
And it is there that you
really mature and that you
develop convolutional neural networks, what?
Really, is this the year?
Yes, yes.
Finally, I had already started in Toronto.
And even in my thesis, actually, I had networks with local connections and all that.
So, it was already a bit there.
But yes, that's where we
actually did it.
And then, Léon, on his side,
was doing a thesis in France.
And he made it work for
speech recognition.
He also worked on
convolutional networks.
And we ended up making products, in fact, that used convolutional networks
for reading checks,
things like that.
The applications... Yes,
for letters, addresses.
Yes, addresses, it has
never been a commercial thing.
It was a prototype.
Ah yes? Ah okay.
But the commercial applications,
the main one,
was for reading
amounts on checks
and things like
that, financial documents.
Yes, reports on
you, really, where we do
the recognition of alphanumeric signs
and everything.
It's really for checks.
And that had a commercial
life between the
mid-1990s and
early 2000s.
But I was no longer involved.
Because from 1996,
in fact, AT&T separated.
And then, it was the early
years of the Internet.
And the part of AT&T that
commercialized these systems
of reading checks, in
fact, was separated from us.
And the patents belonged to them.
And where, physically?
In New Jersey.
And so, you stayed
in New Jersey,
2003-2013, is that right, New
York University, NYU?
I spent a short time
at the NEC Research
Institute, in the large Japanese
company, NEC.
And then, that lab, it kind of fell apart.
So, I left pretty quickly and I
became a professor at NYU in 2003.
And ten years later,
2013, I joined Facebook.
But part-time,
I was still a professor.
I am still a professor at NYU.
Actually, it's quite interesting
because the world of academic research
and the world of research
in the company are quite linked.
In any case, and me, sometimes, I think,
is this the world, the open source,
or in any case, the free sharing
of information, of research,
is this not what
drives, what sometimes obliges companies
to keep a foot in publications
or in this kind of things?
No, in fact, what drives in
large part… No, the direct, the bar.
What drives companies in
large part to have relationships with the university,
in any case, in the United States,
is access to talent.
That is, they want to have
a pipeline, you see, of interns,
to have a relationship with professors who
are working on subjects that interest them,
because you are a good student
who could come and work for us,
and teach us how
to use your methods, etc.
So, it's a really good
reason for the relationship.
And in the United States, doctoral
students, for example,
so there is no equivalent
to the numbers that there are in France.
where doctoral students
can do this on-site, in industry.
There is no such thing in the United States.
But on the other hand, the three months of summer,
students can
do whatever they want.
So, they are not tied to the university.
And most of them will do
internships in industry.
And so, they are a bit like
the bees of American technology.
Because you need to circulate
ideas, techniques.
And one of the things you are also known for,
is that you created the Lab Le
Faire, Facebook AI Research.
You are trying to promote the American model, there.
But no, and in fact,
honestly, today,
I don't know, half of the ecosystem,
well, a good part of
the French ecosystem in AI,
are from Fer.
Anyway, there is a, clearly, Fer mafia.
So, there are quite a few researchers
and engineers who have passed through Fer,
who then went on to
found boxes, etc.
or began to
work in other labs.
But there is also the fact that fer
had a cruising speed until last year.
it had about forty doctoral
students in residence.
So, since the doctorate lasts three years,
that means there were about twelve each year,
who had completed their doctorate at Fer
with access to computing resources, etc.
with access to the best
researchers in the field and everything.
And so, all these people, of course, have completely disrupted the ecosystem.
I think that the creation
of FAIR Paris in 2015.
had a huge effect
on the French ecosystem,
finally, Parisian, in particular
French, in general and in Europe, in fact.
So, it gave ideas
to talented young students
that, in fact, to do a doctorate in AI,
it's the coolest thing they could imagine.
Fifteen years ago, the coolest thing that people were doing
young students
who were graduating from school,
it's about doing the finances.
And that has changed.
It's no longer about finance
now, it's about AI.
We had received Neil Zeghidour, who told us they wanted to do a thesis
and in short, they hadn't necessarily been taken,
but he was told, listen, there is
this thesis... No, no, it's the opposite.
They wanted to write a thesis on
neural networks, at the time,
and there were so few, it hadn't even returned to Hype,
what they told him, well, listen,
if you're really interested, go ahead.
Then, finally, actually, it was...
You, you had seen that 40 years ago, but...
Yes, no, but it's true
that there was a period phase
for the neuron zone between the end
of the 1980s and the mid-1990s.
Then, everyone
lost interest.
It became a bit taboo.
And it has somewhat
reappeared at the end of the 2000s
because of the media battle we had
with Yoshua Bengio and Geoffrey Hinton.
The deep learning, you know.
We renamed this deep learning and
then we mainly proposed new methods.
Then we finally made it work too.
And so, it finally convinced the
communities initially, speech recognition,
then, image recognition, of course.
And then, thirdly,
the understanding of
natural language, what, NLP,
that deep learning, was
really something that worked.
So, it revolutionized these three fields.
But it's true that in France,
in the academic environment, in 2015,
there were practically no one doing it in universities.
They were still... Academics
are a bit conservative.
And then, in France, we like
maths and deep learning,
it's not easy to
do math, you know.
It's not easier if we use methods, like kernel methods,
Bayesian stuff, all that.
One can do beautiful math.
It doesn't work as well, but...
Well, we can write books.
But it's beautiful math, you know.
But these are beautiful mathematics.
How is it that this has become a bit obsolete,
but that there was less interest starting from the early 2000s?
No, it's rather the mid-1990s.
Mid-1990s, what is it due to?
It started to decline in 1996.
Because it was too complicated?
Did it require too much power?
There are many reasons.
I'm not the best person to analyze
that, because I was right in the middle of it,
but I think there are
a combination of reasons.
The first, is that
it is indeed complicated
and there were no tools
software, portable, etc.
that people used.
Everyone used completely different computer platforms.
You couldn't do a neural network on PCs, it's not possible.
It was either Sun workstations,
be it Silicon Graphics,
soit des choses comme
cela, des propriétaires.
There is IRIX, AIX, HPUX,
all that, etc.
So, we were under Sun, then
we switched to Silicon Graphics, after,
because they had a better performance in terms of time.
And there wasn't the software,
there wasn't Python,
there weren't all those gadgets open
source that we could use now.
And the only open source
tool that there was, were things
like GCC, Emacs and others,
but not really for that.
So, actually, we, with Léon, had written
a complete system
with a LISP interpreter,
all at once with
a LISP compiler and all that.
But we couldn't
really exchange our software.
There was no platform,
there was no SourceForge,
there was no GitHub,
there was no Internet.
It happened later.
So, in fact, everyone had to invest
six months, a year to
create a platform
software to make neural networks work.
Most people were making mischief,
because it is very
easy to do silly things
when implementing backprop for the first time,
we do an hour of sign language or something.
So, it was a big
investment for people.
And so, most people
did not want to do that.
So, what were they doing?
They used MATLAB
and then they did something
simple, but building a neural network with MATLAB,
at the time, that wasn't really possible.
There really weren't the tools.
Except for people who
were investing the time in the tools.
What we did with Léon,
that's what gave us
super powers, it was that we made our own tools.
Okay.
And this allowed us to
make convolutional networks,
see how they worked.
A whole graphical library
and all that, of visualization and everything,
which was actually more powerful than what we have today.
In fact, it's amazing.
And so, it meant that there was no communication
that there is now,
which is instantaneous,
where you download the latest
code that is associated to
paper and you can make
the last network turn.
There, one had to spend six months, a year,
to implement something.
So, it really was necessary to believe in it.
That means you had the garbage.
and you would reimplement cleanroom the papers.
There were people who wanted
to reimplement convolutional networks.
There weren't many.
And there was this legend that,
you see, I was more or less
the only one who knew how to make them work,
which was completely wrong.
But it wasn't that complicated.
But it's true that it
required tools.
At the same time, it's the name.
Yann the qu'un.
You see, we believe there's only one.
There's only one.
But that means you had people above you,
in management
at Bell Labs, etc.,
who believed in it, after all, and who weren't afraid
to have the means, the time, for all that?
The way Bell Labs operated.
So, the director of the lab, a
guy named Larry Jackel,
who had created the group in 1985, I think,
based on neural networks.
In fact, he's a physicist, by profession.
And then, he had a new department,
so he wondered what to do.
Because at Bell Labs,
we hired intelligent people, we gave them
the means to succeed,
and we gave them peace.
OK.
It's cool, that.
If he was asking for resources,
obviously, he was asking questions.
But basically,
we let people work on what they wanted.
So, he went completely off track and asked
on what I would have worked,
what is the cool thing.
And he met John Hopfield,
who was a professor at Princeton,
but who had a part-time job at Bell Labs.
It was between Princeton and Caltech.
And he asked me
on what I would have worked.
And John Hopfield said to him.
that he was a physicist,
that he was working on hardware
for neural networks,
special chips for
making neural networks.
This concept is not new.
John Hopfield, a Nobel laureate in physics with Geoffrey Hinton two years ago
for what are called Hopfield and Geoffrey
networks, and Boltzmann machines.
It was originally a biophysicist.
And so Larry got into that.
He hired a few people.
And then I came in in 88.
And then I started working on
convolutional networks pretty quickly.
because I had already
worked on that in Toronto.
They had character-based databases.
And so, in two months, I was there.
I beat all the
performance records
on the
character-based things.
And there was something, a funny story,
it was that before... When
I was still a post-doc in Toronto,
Larry Jackel asked me «
Listen, you're coming in October,
we'd like to order a computer for you,
so that you can work when
you arrive, that it's there when you arrive.
What do you use at the moment ? »
I said « We use a Sun 4,
there's one that just arrived in Toronto,
it's great, all of that, it's a huge flop, it's hallucinatory. »
He says « Ok ».
And then, it was a Sun 4
which was the central server
of the entire IT department.
Ah, so everyone was on a mainframe?
It wasn't a mainframe,
that's what we called a mini-computer.
It is a mini-computer.
Ah, but you mean everyone was involved?
Everyone would be on it.
You had 30 or 40 doctoral students who were connecting to that thing.
Not everyone used it for neural networks,
but it wasn't really...
Was it a timeshare?
It was a unique system, you connect.
So, that's the project I was working on.
I also had a workstation
Sun, but Sun 3 with a 68000.
Amazing.
So, I said to him, "Okay, Sun 4,
it's the one with the Sparc."
The Sparc processors of Sun.
And I arrive at Bell Labs.
and there is a Sun 4,
but just for me !
That means a lot.
That means a lot of
things, the methods we use.
So, well, I'm a bit
skeptical and then I look at Larry.
And then he says, smiling
"You know, at Bell Labs,
you don't become famous
by saving money."
There's a lot to learn from that.
"You don't get famous
by saving money.
Ah, yes, okay.
It's very interesting.
So, if we go back a
little to return a little
more contemporary,
but therefore 2013-2023, that is.
..
2025, no ?
2025, it's the era at Meta.
You received the Turing Award in 2018
which is the
Fields medal or the
Nobel Prize
in computer science, let's
just say so.
Right.
But, so,
at that time, the World Models, there
were already two hypotheses
between LLMs and
World Models.
Does that make sense?
Yes, in a way.
Me, for example, I gave a keynote at NIPS.
It was still called
NIPS at the time,
not yet NeurIPS, in 2016.
My main message at the
end of the speech was
The future of AI
is World Models
So, learning predictive models
of the world, I think, is the key
And then learning actions
and then optimizing
intrinsic objective functions
are really the path forward for
making progress in AI.
They are systems that
are able to predict
what the effect of an
action on the world will be, etc.,
that can be learned in an
autonomous way, and then controlled
by giving them
an objective, etc.
So, I had this
idea a long time ago.
That's even from 2016, it's from before.
But let's say, I started talking about it
publicly, if you want, at that time.
But the research hadn't been successful to... If you want,
we couldn't really
do that in articles
because it was
still just an idea.
And then,
for several years,
I have had research projects both at Meta and at NYU,
to Meta for
training models,
which could have been
World Models
through video prediction.
In fact, it never worked.
So, we tried to make it work
until, I don't know, 2021,
something like that.
Generative models
for video prediction.
It never worked
for,
as a model
of the world, in fact,
to predict what will happen.
Maybe to create
generations of videos,
but even at that time, it didn't work because we didn't have
the diffusion models or anything like that.
Therefore,
according to you, because it's just a bad
representation of the world, right?
No,
it's the fact that most of the
information in a video is unpredictable.
The bulk of the information in
a video is unpredictable.
If I take,
here, the people who are watching
see only a small part of the room,
they may have a vague idea of the surroundings if you turn the camera,
but you cannot predict the details, you cannot say that,
outside the camera's field of view,
there is a video game that is in the process of... little dinosaurs dancing.
There is a T-Rex, etc.
There are all the people with security here.
There is no way you can
predict all the details at the pixel level
of what is in the video if
the camera starts to turn.
Who could have predicted?
The vast majority of the information in a video
or in any
real-world signal
is unpredictable.
So, if we try to train
a generative model to hallucinate
that is not predictable,
it doesn't work
very well at the end.
And therefore, the crucial idea
on which we are working for
world models called JEPA,
Joint Intermediate
Predictive Architecture,
in French,
predictive architecture
of joint hunting.
It's nice.
Joint hunting.
What are you doing, hunting?
No, that's beautiful.
It's beautiful, it's beautiful.
So, the idea of that,
is that we train a system to
find an abstract representation
of the input signal,
let's say,
the video that
the information
that we can predict and which
eliminates all the things
that we cannot predict.
And that, is absolutely crucial
for a whole bunch of reasons.
We can come back to that if you want,
but it's a bit technical or philosophical.
So, that's the idea of JEPA,
it's nothing else.
So, this replaces a generative architecture that predicts everything, in fact, everything.
And for discreet tokens,
it works because it's easy
managing uncertainty
in forecasting.
All the space is finite.
You only have a finite number of tokens, you can
predict a probability
for each possible token
and then,
through autoregressive prediction,
have a not-so-bad estimate
of a probability of a sequence.
That's how LLMs work.
But if it's a
continuous and noisy world,
it doesn't work at all, but not at all.
So,
that means we cannot use
generative AI for the real world.
So, when I tell everyone to abandon generative AI,
I don't do that
with friends, let's say.
But it's an objective,
abandonner l'IA générative
to predict
for world models
or a human-type intelligence.
Okay,
if we want systems that understand
the real world, the physical world,
which is much more complex
than language or code,
then we actually need
non-generative models.
Can you explain, I don't know,
30 seconds really
for our listeners,
what is a world
model and what is,
well,
what is not a world model?
Good question.
Actually, when people talk about
machine learning,
AI,
generative, diffusion,
and then,
world model, what is it?
What is different
and what is similar?
Yeah,
so,
world model,
it is becoming
a kind of buzzword.
That's the problem.
That's why, if you can define it,
it's definitely much better.
And there are many people who
want to say different things
by the phrase world model.
And in fact, there are many
boxes that say they do it,
but actually,
they don't.
In fact, it's a
rather typical joke.
Well, we're in French, so
we can tell bad jokes.
Especially, especially.
It stays in France.
Yeah.
World model,
is like
sex among adolescents.
Teenage sex.
Teenage sex,
that is to say.
everyone is talking about it,
no one is doing it.
It's more complicated than that.
Ah yes.
Everyone is talking about it,
everyone says that he does it.
Ah yes.
But actually,
nobody knows what
it is and nobody does it.
Ah yes, there are different
levels of depth.
"It stays in France!"
So what is it?
So,
given the state of
the world at the moment.
and given an action
that I imagine taking,
can I predict
the state of the world at this moment
+1 after I have.
executed this action.
So, that means it's physics
potentially?
Does it mean understanding 3D?
Understanding...
No, not necessarily.
It can be anything because
it's not necessarily 3D.
It's abstract in fact.
It's completely abstract.
If we're playing a 2D platform video game, like this one, it's not 3D.
A great game.
This is not 3D.
But we also build ourselves... So
it can be... Can we say
what is the passage
of correlation
to causality?
One can,
but there isn't really a very
sophisticated method for establishing causality.
It's just state,
action, following state.
That doesn't mean I've
made a video game engine.
No.
So not at all, not at all, because
we're not going to produce pixels.
We are going to... You will produce an
abstract representation of the world.
An abstract
representation
of the world.
After that, you must,
within quotes,
if you want to use
pixels or speed
or an electric current
or anything.
There are absolutely no tokens,
there is no
discretization at all.
And it's not something...
We have a world model in our head,
but that's also the case with our
cat or even a Parisian rat.
But as a result,
a question that I ask myself,
is that you have to create,
this abstract model
in the latent space.
Yes.
And so, you have a subject
of... So,
in LLMs, this is called
tokenization, but ultimately,
you have a transformation
and therefore, an interpretation.
Perhaps first, an acquisition.
then successive layers of interpretation
to end with a latent space.
Yes.
On which, afterwards,
you can work.
On which you can... With
which you can make predictions.
And above all,
In addition,
I imagine that there is an
infinite number, but in
any case, a large number of paths between.
..
If I say that I take the cup and bring
it there, I can
do that, I can do that.
There is a probability
distribution.
No, these are not
probabilities, necessarily.
Not even?
No, not at all.
No, but on the other hand,
it's intuitive physics
that we learn when we
are babies, that all animals also learn.
They all have a role model in their head that gives them the ability to plan.
and that allows us to say
if I push on this glass,
at the base, it will slide.
If I push upwards,
it might slide, might
tip over, I don't know,
it depends on
the friction of the thing.
If I push, with the same force
on the table, it won't move.
There's a lot, actually, we learn
a quantity of knowledge,
of understanding the
functioning of the world
in the first months of life, which is absolutely incredible.
and that's what allows us, at the end,
when one reaches the age of 4 or 5 years,
to accomplish a whole bunch of tasks that
would be extremely complex for a robot
that most robots are
not at all capable of executing,
even less to perform without
being explicitly trained to do so
and then, what allows a 10-year-old child
to behave almost like an adult
in a whole bunch of situations or a
17-year-old teenager learning to drive
in about fifteen
hours of practice.
We don't know how to do that.
It's your responsibility.
He takes it every time, you give it to him
and he makes it fall.
for a few months of his life.
It's just to see.
He trains his model
of representation.
Or your cat,
he picks up the glass and makes
your glass fall once.
That, it's just to make sure there isn't a template.
It's just to
know that it's the pattern.
So, that means that there is a form associated with it.
which is a bit of empiricism.
and rather than
of theorization or of
discovery of the rules but of
in a completely
abstract way, not at all quantifiable.
No, but above all, that a rat
or a cat is capable of doing.
So, it's not
to understand physics
by writing equations.
That's right.
It's understanding
intuitive physics.
through experience,
through observation and in fact, it's much
more complex but it allows you to model
phenomena much
more complex than
that we can model
by writing equations.
For example,
there are certain cases
where I could write equations
but it is completely useless.
For example,
if I wanted to predict what will happen between us in a minute,
what I could do,
it is to measure the wave function of the universe
in a cubic kilometer around us
and then to make a large
quantum simulation of all the states
of all the electrons
of the entire theory
quantum field theory
everything, all the spins, etc.
it would simulate our
brains and that is the interest
to predict what one will
tell in a minute.
Some nonsense.
And that would work.
And then it would work
but only once.
It's not possible because we cannot first measure the wave function
of the universe secondly, in fact, that wouldn't be an exact prediction because.
this cube of the universe is interacting
with the rest of the galaxy and even the rest
from the universe due to intrigues
so it wouldn't actually be possible
there would be unpredictable phenomena
that would happen.
so very quickly the simulation
would diverge from reality because
we cannot model all of that, and then
well, we would need a quantum computer
the head of the galaxy
to do that, so it's not worth it.
Well, so what do we
do, we invent abstractions
the abstraction that is above
quantum theory
fields is the theory
of elementary particles
or the atomic theory.
or chemistry, molecules, etc.
biochemistry maybe but even
that we're not going to simulate our brains
with biochemistry, it's not
possible, we don't know how to do it
and that would be too complicated
so above that there is
what are the organelles in
cells, the cells.
organs, organisms, and
then actually, the right level to simulate
what might happen
predict a little bit of
what will happen in a
minute is psychology.
and is a level of description
of the universe, or rather, of reality, which is
more dense in information, perhaps
which is much more abstract
so, which does not contain all the details
of the movement of all the molecules
but which, on the other hand, allows
to make predictions over a longer period
but this means that
when I create a world model, it
is necessary to think about
what level of abstraction
on va travailler, c'est-à-dire que donc, en fait, c'est-à-dire que ce n'est pas
je vais prendre, je fais
un world model, donc je
prends trois, quatre
dimensions, l'espace-temps etc.
donc là, je choisis une abstraction qui va
être, en fait, plus compliqué que ça
because the system must
not only choose the level of abstraction
but also learn the correct
representation, of course
so all the ingenuity, all the choice is
here, that is, to learn
representations of the world that allow
to make predictions, there are thousands
of types of world
model, it is possible
full full but in fact when one thinks
this is the basis of deep learning
the deep learning all the problem
of deep learning and what has obsessed me for
45 years is how to find
good
representations of the world
that allow to make
predictions
until now, we knew how to do that for
very well deep learning
we stack layers, we train something
to recognize images, speech etc
or predict the next token in a text
it works very well because predict
the next token is to learn
the classifications in fact
it works very well for that
to learn hierarchical representations for
a particular task
learn a supervised
or self-supervised
task, especially for LLMs
but how to do this more generally
for world models in which
we don't just want to
find a representation
that allows to.
recognize images or something
but that is conditioned on actions.
so that it allows to predict what
will happen and in the end it gives us
an abstract representation, not
just observation of the world
but also of action, the whole
problem is how to act
people are talking about agentic systems
right now, it's also a big buzzword
it was a big buzzword last year
and I don't understand how people
can think or imagine
that they will build
agentic systems
that will work.
without these systems having the ability to
predict the consequences of their actions.
it's completely stupid it can't work that's just it
a collective hallucination, if that's possible
walk the same way as one can take
a little guy who knows nothing about cooking and making him follow a recipe
I don't feel like a great chef at all
behind the kitchen, I feel like I am
all of a sudden, anyone can
learn how to make a recipe
provided that you follow the recipe, so
agentic systems at the moment
are trained to follow
recipes but in fact
when they do a
stupid thing they don't know it
and the little boy has just learned
to make a complicated sauce
sometimes it doesn't work
he doesn't know why.
that's the fundamental
thing
it's to have
as many recipes as possible.
but without really understanding
the interaction
between the ingredients, we just
you've done it well today when you use
Claude or ChatGPT the number of times
it tells you something, and you ask it
questions afterwards, and you realize
that in fact it told you nonsense
and even it realizes itself.
there are big debates, you know, about
the actual issue of going to
information to train
enterprise workflow models
and so it's
stacking the recipes
and then somehow we have a function
of average in the middle and that works
not too bad, but
intelligence isn't like that
it is knowledge, it is not
intelligence, that is knowledge, that is knowledge
so it's the reproduction of knowledge
how to say procedural empirical empirical
but which already exists, which has been
developed by someone else
like the apprentice cook
who applies the recipe.
but who creates the recipe.
and intelligence
it's not a collection
of knowledge.
or an accumulation of
declarative knowledge.
it's not even a collection of skills
on which we have learned the recipes.
it's rather the ability to
invent new recipes
or when faced
with a new problem
to adapt very quickly, like learning
to drive in about fifteen hours
where the first time one
faces a problem
new we can thanks
to our world model
find a sequence of actions that will
accomplish the task, just a question
but isn't it because
I see them coming in the comments
is there not, let's say, a sort of in-between, but in any case, to move on from the subject
stochastic parrots, actually
you see, for example, for an LLM
in the tokens there is a
form of information that.
at the scale
no longer exists in discrete
form of tokens but in the latent space
that is, whether it is
rules, patterns, finally you see
everything we can imagine
and therefore the interaction between them.
exists in the time space
and therefore, you see, it is more than
just the repetition of patterns but
somewhere somehow
it's there.
somewhere somehow.
he manages to draw it if you
want, here's a form of a ruler yes.
and so, in fact, you see
the interaction, I don't know.
if we add sugar
it's sweeter.
it doesn't appear.
it doesn't appear in
the text precisely but
in the latent space
it eventually takes shape
in any case, what to describe
and so, in fact
when it goes down again.
well, you see
we manage to find a
form of intelligence
so yes and no.
because the problem of the LLM is
that the only communication of information
from one calculation step to another
it's through an ah, discreet token
it doesn't stay in the latent space
it's 3 bytes, yeah, okay
a token is essentially 3 bytes
not even
you produce 1 byte
you move it into
the input context and therefore the information
which is communicated between one
calculation step and the next.
a symbol that can be stored in 2
or 3 bytes and if it was the latent space
so that we could re-inject it, there were people to ensure discretion
soit done, de manière asynchrone, donc on va
tenter de le faire, par exemple, à mon avis
the best way to do that is
JEPA
- What a chance!
- That's the idea, that's the idea
you are making a prediction
in the latent space.
and you never try to rebuild
the entered space because if the entered
is based on natural data
it's not possible, I agree
for tokens, you could, if
they are text sequences
you can indeed
return to the original space
so there are models like
a bit of a hybrid between the two
that try to make predictions
at the level of presentation
but are still trained
at the end, to predict the tokens, so you have
models like state-space models
for example, in which the internal and linear dynamics, which is a bit limited
and then there are models
like coconut there are
two or three like that, in which you have
a little bit of prediction in a space
not discreet, but eventually we discretize anyway, okay, and at the end
well, it's a bit of an LLM, otherwise the other
method to get out of the constraints
self-aggressive prediction
of symbols, it's you who manage
in order for your system to produce many
possible sequences of symbols and then
you have a second one that evaluates them and gives you the best one
it's a bit like that the code generation system works but it's a form
of quantization, because you
quantize the latent space, it's a form
of reasoning, it is a form of
agreement, reasoning
it's a completely different topic, but the reasoning.
cannot be cannot
be done by prediction
auto-regressive means when we reason
we don't do it by producing words one after the other, we think, we internalize
in our latent space it remains in
the latent space it remains in the latent space
we manipulate mental models
etc so for example I'm sure that there are
many geeks looking at us but
well it's a high school math level
it's fine I tell you
I pose the question give
me a family of three
vectors in the plane.
which are linearly
independent.
so you think.
what is your answer, and I
don't have to ask you, I have seen
three vectors in the
two-dimensional plane.
in two dimensions
in the plane in the plane.
which are linearly independent
give me a family of three vectors
independent non independent
independent ah pardon, we did well
to not find
a solution, yes you did well
but what's interesting
is the mental process
so most people
I don't know if that's the case for you
but most people certainly
many people who listen to us
form a kind of mental image
of the situation ah yes and then
we think "yes yes" and then everyone else
in fact it's a combination of the two others yes so it's not possible
you hesitated to answer but
you already had the answer
cause of this mental image
we manipulate the mental image
okay
there is of course another way to
do this, which is to say ah but we
there is of course a theorem that
tells you that you can't have
more than n vectors in dimension
n that are independent.
but nobody does that, everyone
starts with the mental image
so it's this story
of a mental model of the world
who is important
so now
in math, in particular, and also for writing code
and maybe for the legal text, I don't know what
a large part of the reasoning can
be done in the field of symbols
when we do math, we do
derivatives, we manipulate symbols
and a part of the
reasoning that makes it
results from symbol manipulation
when writing code very often
we start to write the code and then
this helps us understand the formulation in fact
the abstractions that
we need etc
these are areas
the code and the maths
where the manipulation
of symbols is the substrate
of reasoning in any case a
possible substrate of reasoning not all
these are the two applications for LLMs
I really think so, yes, so
I have a question because there was
about a year ago, a year and a half ago
you talked about it too
but I was talking a lot, you
knew about reasoning
in latent space
and I said I think
that in a year or
two years, that's the case for LLMs anyway
whether reasoning will happen in latent space or
it's about a year and a half after
it's still done in tokens
and secondly, reasoning based on energy, so the idea of minimizing
actually, energy, but while still remaining
in latent space. I've tried
with ZML to re-inject latent space, it doesn't work at all
but so, in your opinion
since we are on this
why isn't it something that
is pushed, because it could be
from my point of view, it could be a
win, at least a incremental gain
we would still be in the world
of LLMs, where everyone is happy
but one would still have more interesting arguments, because today
it's really raw, forced
- the real question is how
to make it work, that is, the thing
who really surprised everyone after Transformers
what architectures should I use that will really work in the beginning
these were encoder-decoder architectures, similar to BERT.
where you take a piece of text
and pass it through an encoder
before that, you mask
certain words
some text and then you train a large
encoder-decoder neural network.
in which the decoder is autoregressive
after saying the missing words
and then finally we realized that to really
scale and
get something working
it was necessary to remove the encoder and
just train a decoder.
and this decoder, you don't train it by taking a sequence of symbols
and by removing in
masking inputs
you build the architecture
in such a way that
that it is strictly
causal, that is to say that
in order to predict an output, you cannot
look at the corresponding input token
you can only look at those that are to its left.
so the architecture
of the system itself
makes it so that there is a kind of implicit masking
that when you give it a sequence
it can only look at the first
half of the sequence to predict a token
and so in fact
this is the GPT architecture.
and you simply train
this thing
to reproduce its input
on its output, okay.
it's an autoencoder
in fact a GPT, okay
ok that doesn't say
it's an autoencoder
and in world models you also have
different architectures
which have encoders, some don't have encoders so in
the correct way to
make world models
it's the same thing, that is
you predict it's not a
token but a vector, right
ok, based on what precedes but
you do this in a placement space
that is, there is
first a layer
that takes the sequence
that encodes it, and then it's this
sequence that you pass through something
a bit like GPT, but which is
in any case strictly causal.
that you can train it means
that this sequence becomes a vector.
it's not a sequence of
vectors like in the case of an LLM.
so it's a sequence of vectors
but not a sequence of tokens.
ah yes, okay.
you don't need to tokenize, you can take
the video and so also so you have the same
you use an encoder, you work on it, an encoder produces
a sequence if the input is a
sequence, it produces a sequence too.
of representation
of each input, which each
can also take multiple inputs
so, if you
give video, for example
your encoder can
take, I don't know, 16 or 64
frames as input and produce a
representation for that which is not necessarily
a vector that itself can be a
good choice ok, so that's it and that's a.
It's an object
in the sequence.
and this sequence you train
an architecture that we call a
causal predictor.
that simply reproduces the input on its
output because, as mentioned in the paper.
the world model that you published in 2025.
you are talking a little about that, so if we understand the paper.
there is a latent space
there is an analysis of the situation and
it creates a bit of a problem or a projection
of the latent space under a latent subspace, the weights are a bit
are a bit modified
or at least projected
and there it's funny because
there is a function
a Gaussian function
that you apply
me, I was rediscovering
the wave function
you see the wave function in physics, I
thought, but is there a connection
or absolutely not, no, there is no
connection to physics in this regard
finally, not with the
wave functions, not with
quantum mechanics
in any case, not yet
but soon, not yet, not yet there in
the video, there is yours, she transforms
world models into quantum ones and there, in
one year, she will accept her Nobel Prize and everything
I thank Mehdi Mejari because, well, not of quantum ok, that's the problem.
That's the problem that needs to be solved when training a JEP.
And it's an argument that people use against this idea of JEP, okay.
It's that there can be what is called in good French a collapse.
Okay.
The problem is the following
we take, let's say, a part
of a video that we encode
and then the second part
of the video that we encode
and then we try to train a
predictor to predict the representation
of the second
part based on the
representation of the
first part. It can very
easily
if we train it to minimize
prediction error.
it can decide to completely ignore the input and produce representations
constants that do not
depend on the input and
so, here the problem
of prediction is trivial
and so the thing comes back and tells you
your prediction error is zero
you did well, but in fact it doesn't
work because it's a collapse
you found a good translation, it's a
collapse, a collapse, that's why
that you send a Gaussian
a little to create different paths
with different probabilities, then it's there
that we start digging in the trench
self-supervised learning in joint embedding in joint hunting
and it's something on which
my first papers
that dates back to 1993
so you see, it's not 93?
yeah yeah
oh my god, how old were you in 93
How old were you or I was 9
ok, I'll explain the problem
it's very simple, we had this problem
at AT&T, some people who are Venus
and who said, "We would like to store a signature."
of someone who signs on a
tablet but on the magnetic tape
they didn't have a chip card, at the time, in the United States.
and there are 80 bytes on
a magnetic tape
how can one store the representation
of a signature in 80 bytes
ah, good idea, let's take
a neural network
a convolutional network where
they provide the sequence
some points, someone who signs, and then
it's a convolutional network and then at the end.
we organize an outing
with 80 participants.
80 values, a vector of 80
dimensions that will be quantized on 8 bits
so, that's it
someone has made a signature, how
can we verify that this signature
it certainly comes from that person,
we will train this neural network.
we don't know in advance
we don't have the collection
of all the signatures
of all the people
so, it must work for any signature, what we are going to do
it's about training a network of
neurons so that when we give it
two signatures of
the same person
it outputs the same
80-component vector.
and when we give it a signature of
a person and a signature of another person
or a signature of another
person who is trying to imitate the first
this gives us different vectors
learning is completely trivial
now we call this
contrastive learning
but what it means is you put two
signatures if it's two
signatures the same person
you have a cost function that says attract all
these two vectors
to each other of course.
if you do that
it collapses due to a collapse
because the thing ignores
completely the input, which produces a Constant vector.
so you have
contrasting examples
which are signatures that are different
our sequences are different and here
you push the two
vectors away from each other
okay you push them away from each other, okay
so, this is the contracting production
it is used
absolutely everywhere today
for in LLMs, the LLMs
when they analyze
an image actually use
most of them not all
most of them use perception pipelines that are trained
with a method
that is called clip.
which is a thing that has been proposed
by OpenAI a few years ago
but in fact, that's it, it's the same
thing, meaning that you show an image.
and instead of showing another
another image, a signature.
you show a textual description
of this image and you say I will
an embedding of text is an
embedding of the image. If the text
is a good description of the image
I bring them closer together
and you have contrasting examples or
you have a description of another image.
and there you push them apart, it's
a bit guided by the loss function
by the loss function, the loss function which has two terms, one attractive
and one repulsive, which says the things
that I know are identical
semantically, I bring them closer
and the things that are different
I push them away, there are many ways
to do that, it makes me think maybe
the contrastive side makes me think of what Inton proposed a few years ago
so there is a model
that is called SimCLR
S-I-M-C-L-R which is a thing
that is contrastive and was one of the first
convolutional networks
that were actually contrastive
that gave reasonable performance on clear images
me, in fact, I had tried
to revive the method
that is called
this: the networks, if to me.
using contrastive methods
also in the middle of the 2000s
with two students of mine, Sumit Chopra and
and Raia Hadsel, and who inspired
a lot of work
after, in fact, the system of
face recognition
which was used by Facebook
until they stopped doing
face recognition
it was actually fine-tuned with this kind
of method, so you show
two images, two photos of the same
person, the representations are attracted
and then two photos of different people, you push them apart, it must be
when they resemble each other, they converge, and
when they don't resemble each other, they diverge.
otherwise, you have false positives all the
time, otherwise, you have false positives all the
time.
where the thing collapses completely
so, CLIP, the C of CLIP, is contrastive.
I have a question
about how they are trained.
today, the models
what are they, are they videos
I have seen datasets about Robocasa, which are
robots that are in 3D kitchens
some do it with video games
with Unreal engines, or even Atari, I've seen things, Minecraft, some people are trying
train the models with Minecraft
there are real videos
from the physical world, it's
how do we train
today a model of the world
in the JEPA sauce.
so, before I
answer these questions
I'll remind you about that
in a minute.
I need to explain to you the
alternatives to contrastive methods.
The
training methods of JEPA.
Or of Joint Embedding, so methods in
which there is no reconstruction.
In which you have to find a
representation space in which you can
make predictions
and avoid collapse
so I talked about
contrasting methods
that prevent the collapse
but in fact they are not effective, that is to say that
when trying to train
using a contrastive method
some rather complete representations
of images or things like that
in fact, we can't manage to make the
representation fill the entire space
regarding representation, we always have somewhat degenerate representations.
and then it requires a huge number of contrasting examples, so there is another series.
there are two other
categories of methods.
one of which are methods
that are called distillation.
so they are used by papers
that we have published called IJEPA VJEPA.
BYOL from DeepMind
and DINO from FAIR Paris.
so, these are
distillation methods.
and there were others before, like
SimCLR etc.
Not SimCLR, MoCo.
Distillation... like in LLMs?
So distillation is...
the distillation method is a kind of strange thing
also, you have two encoders, so you take
one input and another input which can
be a corrupted version of the first
or it can be a different piece
of the video etc you pass them
through encoders which
are identical in
architecture and then you try to predict
the representation of
the original input
of that which has been corrupted
or transformed etc.
and therefore DINO walks
on this principle.
IJEPA too
and the way one
prevents the collapse
it's that we
don't propagate gradients backwards
that on one side
that is to say, there is
one side where the encoder
does not receive the gradient.
and its weights are not
updated by gradient.
and the weights of this
encoder in fact are
a kind of moving average
on the weights of the other
which is trained
and for some mysterious reason it does not collapse
why mysterious?
mysterious because we don't
have the theory that explains it yet
it works but we
don't know why
it works but we don't know why, real engineering like we like it
if it's not broken, don't touch it, if I ain't broke
don't fix it no no the research is
we know what, but it doesn't work
and the engineering, it works but we
don't know why, while here we are
it doesn't work here, it doesn't
work, we don't know why, there is
one or two theoretical papers that
try to explain that the dynamics
of learning in this case have fixed points that are not collapsed etc.
but well, it's a bit
like broke and good.
there are disadvantages
to using these methods.
but they work and
they work at scale.
and so the models of
video, the VJEPA that we trained
on large amounts of
data, it works very well.
but it's not satisfactory so the
method that we use in the world model
which is a method called SIGReg
which means Sketched Isotropic
Gaussian Regularization
and so you
will tell us in French
ah yes that's a
question about
regularization then wait
what is the first
Gaussian regularization
Gaussian isotropic but the
sketch there is no French word drawn
yes it is by projection
by projected by by
by drawing projected by
projection intersection.
Gaussian regularization
isotropic by by projection multiple yes
like this like this go
this is an exclusivity
not bad, either
it is totally French, it is
completely new, it says in 10 seconds
it's just out of the
oven the French Academy is
and furthermore, it's happening, we need to call, we need to call the Quebecers
It is called the Quebec office
technology
it's part of a
technical class
actually we have discovered
several and then well
sure Jürgen Schmidhuber
says he invented that in 1990
but actually there are some papers
that date from the 80s
by Geoffrey Hinton and Sue Becker
who are based on the idea
who is to say if we have
something like that
doesn't rebuild
so it can collapse
we are going to try to maximize the amount of information that is released
encoders, we are going to try to find a measure
which measures the
amount of information.
so there's a big problem with that, which is
that we don't know how to measure the information
because to measure
information with all the definitions
it is necessary to know the
probability distribution
in a continuous
high-dimensional space
try to find a probability distribution
from samples
this is an ultra complicated
problem that we absolutely do not know how to solve
which is mathematically
intractable which is more complicated
than all machine learning
so it's not worth it.
so we don't know how to calculate the information
we can only make approximations
and there's a big problem that
all the approximations we can make
is estimating the amount
of information in a series of vectors.
it's just overestimations.
it's just upper bands
not lower bands.
and we want to maximize
if we want to maximize something and we have a lower band
we push on the lower band, it increases the quantity.
but if we only have upper bands
and we pull on them, we don't know at all
if it goes according to plan
then we'll do it anyway
and we'll cross our fingers, so it's also a bit of engineering, that's what I love
but there are also a bit of maths behind it
so the idea is how
to make sure we can pass a certain number of examples through the encoder and then
what we are going to recover
is a kind of matrix
for each example, we have a representation vector, and then for all the examples
what we have is a line, so
we end up with a matrix, each line
there is an increase
of a vector
each column is a variable
for all examples of agreement
how to maximize information
what's in this matrix then
first, if all the values are equal
there is no information so
we must make sure for example
all the lines are
different that's
a contrastive method
you say, here is an example, there is a
second example, it is different
make sure that the
two increases are
different that's
a contrastive method
the methods, a little new
like Cy, it's rather the opposite
that is, we are trying to make sure that the columns are different.
it means that each variable.
vehicle, a different piece of information, agreed
so, we had an initial idea, you
can't do that with rotations
simply then you can
do this by measuring correlations
so we actually had two methods, the
first method that I myself found interesting
that these things could
walking that we called
that we called Barlow Twins
Barlow's twins are okay
Barlow is a monster in
theoretical neurosciences
who based much of his theories on
information maximization stories
coding efficiency etc He was
a post-doc working with me at Meta
who was called Stéphane
Denis, a Frenchman
who is now a professor in
Finland and the idea is to de-correlate
the columns of this matrix
making them orthogonal.
so it has to do with making the
covariance matrix of the data
so you take this matrix and
multiply it by its transpose
this gives you a
covariance matrix
and you make sure that it is diagonal
That is, there are
1s on the diagonal of 0s
And this creates variables that all have
a variance of 1 and are uncorrelated
Now, uncorrelated does not mean independent.
So, we have a second method
called VC regularization (VICReg)
variance covariance
regularization, which is a
method
simplified of Barlow
Twins, which works very well
with Adrian Bard, who is a former
PhD student resident at FAIR.
co-supervised by
Jean Ponce and me.
he didn't finish at Google, he has
become a researcher at FAIR.
and there, for a few weeks, he is at
AmiLabs
- Ah! Very good!
- Google has had Bard
they have had Bard, that's why I thought
is it him who gave the name?
does it mean
that the work on the world
models is a more mathematical
that transformer models, diffusion,
LLM, is there a dimension?
diffusion, there's also math, it's
more physics actually, physics
but does that mean that here
you have a mathematical dimension
on vector spaces, a bit
more complicated, does it mean
let's say that there is, there is, every spectrum, there are theories, theories, there are maths.
the theory, the theory that
is not yet too finished.
well, if it's rather Randall
Balestriero who is the first author of.
not LeWorldModel but
LeJEPA which is the paper before.
he is quite involved in
that aspect, he is also French
he is a professor at Brown
he is also affiliated
with AmiLabs and
so there are maths and then there is
indeed engineering and DIY
and screwdrivers, and then he manages to make
it work... So the idea of SIGReg
it means we don't just want to de-correlate the variables, but we want to make them
statistically independent and
and it's much more complicated.
and we don't know how to measure the statistical dependence
of two variables, well, we don't know
measure the statistical dependence
between two variables
okay
or even that of a.
in high dimension
it's very complicated.
so this idea, I had an idea
vague and then Randall actually.
completely took the idea
ran at 100 km/h with
that is to say
if we have a collection of
points, then we can see this matrix
as a collection
of points in a space.
how to make sure these points move so that in the end there is a distribution
gaussian, isotropic, which means that it is gaussian
in all directions
with the same variance
and there is a theorem that says that if a
if a a distribution is gaussian
in this way, in fact, it's the distribution
who has the most
information
for a given variance, well, that's not a very strong argument
but it is interesting, anyway
and then there is a second theorem which
is much more interesting, which says that
if all the projections, so we take the
points and project them according to a dimension
what we will obtain is a
one-dimensional distribution.
if all the projections, so
all the marginal distributions
of a distribution
in high dimension
in all directions
are all gaussian.
the joint distribution is
gaussian so idea
we are going to do many
projections of the points that we
have and we are going to make sure
to move the points
according to all these directions so that the
unidimensional distribution is gaussian
and we know how to do this
that is, we know how to calculate
in one dimension the distance
between an empirical distribution
which is given by points.
and an ideal distribution
which could be gaussian or anything.
we can calculate a distance
and not only that we
can calculate the gradient
of this distance so
it means that we know
in what direction
and by how much
move each point.
according to each projection in such a way that the marginal distribution
in that direction is Gaussian
and in that one too.
and then there is a
third theorem that says
well, actually you don't need to project
on all dimensions if your function
is a bit rigid in
fact you only need
a subset, you don't need a
number of dimensions exponential
depending on
the number of projections
exponentially depending on the dimension
and so it works
super well and then there
aren't many parameters to adjust etc
but it's not
perfect, what's missing.
in this technique it is
the fact that we give it to him beforehand.
a dimension that must
be filled with points.
and there is no reason
that the input distribution
in fact, fill all these dimensions
so, there will need to be a way to adapt
the dimensions automatically that the system
automatically discovers the dimensions
intrinsic characteristics of the variety that contains all the input data.
on the one hand, and on the other hand, it is quite possible that one cannot reduce
this distribution follows a Gaussian
so for example if I take
images
of objects
from all possible angles
if I take
megapixel photos
of this object from all possible
angles ok so
each image is a vector
with one million dimensions
it is a point in
a space
of one million dimensions.
the path followed
by all these points
as I
rotate the object.
it is a very complicated
path in this space of one million dimensions.
but topologically it is a circle
it is a circle because you are able
to project orthogonally on
each one, because you know that you will return
at your starting point because once
you have turned 360 degrees you come
back to your starting point we
are playing, we are playing, we
are playing, so it's
elegant, it's elegant yes
it's a trajectory that is horribly
wobbly, and it's not at all
a circle but it is topologically
assimilable to a circle that is to say that
you shoot at it without breaking
anything and it becomes a circle.
now if I
do it like this.
and like this.
it will be a somewhat complicated thing
it will actually be a sphere but it remains
yes, that's it, but there's a third dimension where I didn't rotate
and therefore that means that this one
it's open, so it's going to be a hit
a little cylinder
in fact, it's a bit about
this theme which were the
papers of 2005-2006
with my students Sumit Chopra, Raia Hadsell.
Raia Hadsell who is director
research at
DeepMind, by the way
so...
she really messed up her career
manifestation!
Non, elle est incroyablement talentueuse.
Donc en fait, c'est des mathématiques assez avancées
of high dimension but we fall back on things that we know with
not tricks but with forms or geometry
- Conceptually anyway
with geometry
- but there are problems on
which we are working
at the moment, which is how to
modify SIGReg and similar things
in order for the system to automatically
discover the topology of the input data.
and the intrinsic dimension
we have a few ideas about that, we have some things that work to some extent, but there is still
there's work to be done, it's not a solved problem
Time passes quickly, we have three more points
There is one: training data.
Today's training data
we see lots of videos, we see companies that force people
to put on helmets
to register with the
hands, we see people
who generate videos
of everyday life, tennis balls
that are hit in all directions, we see labs
that are made with where there is
need, we give the X, Y, Z
with the force in Newton
to really feed
the models, so really very supervised
we see video games
3D, today, what is an ecosystem? A little bit of...
and what is needed for
games, not models. The reason
why people use games to train models.
This is done a lot at
DeepMind, for example, and
then there are other
people who believe in this.
the reason they use
video games is that video games.
since the data is
synthetic and captures in
the entire state of the world, you
can predict pixels.
that is, there is no
uncertainty in the real world.
or predict pixels is
not completely stupid.
and so we can use
a bit classic generative models
to train
world models
by pixel prediction
but this doesn't work for
real video but is it not
the person who lost their keys
outside in the dark
and which go under the light because it is
lit and that they are looking for it there
that's kind of it, it's
because they work in pixels
they generate pixels, and it's basically
only for video games.
so that's one of the reasons why
people are using videos
or on videos of robot simulations
finally, synthetic things because here
there aren't all the impossible textures
and the noise that there is in the real world
there isn't also a story of
capturing the state of the whole world
because in video games you can
capture the world as a whole unit
that you want, but it's not a sensor problem, we have all the sensors.
we don't learn like
video games, well, the thesis is to say.
if we make models that learn
like we learn, like a cat learns.
like a child learns
like an adult learns
we don't need to know everything
can the world become
a good video game thanks to that
for Elon, that could be cool
he needs to pay
people for example, there is something
that at some point
you still have to return
not for everything of course, but still, there is an equation in quite a few.
you see, you learn physics
by throwing a ball, then.
you learn it like that, you offer it, but you eventually come back.
do you come back somewhere
to a real mathematical equation
or somewhere we don't care
actually, that's the cat, it doesn't understand
equations, the Schrödinger cat.
it understands equations but not
two, is there an equation
to create data to just
inject into the model each gutter
has a very, very, very good predictive model of its own dynamics.
it falls back on its paws, it doesn't
know Newton's Christmas.
finally, he doesn't know them, but he knows them
that is to say, he has his
representation, but he doesn't know
it means that this place says I
didn't need this assumption, well
exactly agree, but he doesn't
need to write a few equations
that it can integrate etc
however it has a template
he has a phenomenological model of his
own dynamics which is incredibly
more complicated than
anything we can write
on the dynamics of a robot because there is the elasticity of the tendons of the muscles
some things, well, it's insane complexity
we don't know how to do it, we just know how to write
dynamic equations
of a humanoid robot
and it's because all
the joints are very stiff
we know the characteristics of
all the actuators we've made a lot of noise
of course, and it's
like that for all the demos
robots
humanoid making kung fu
it's because we can write
the equations of dynamics
we don't know all the coefficients
so we just have this through reinforcement learning or through simulation
but all of that is pre-calculated and there
we see it behind videos of robots
that perform demonstrations then
they hit people in the audience
because they don't have the person
they just need to not see the public too
you are cute, but it reminds me of
the chess player Capablanca said
I calculate that with one move she
will advance, but it's always the best move
This is almost like a physical equation in fact
loses information since it's a
simplification, that's it, okay.
anyway, yes, I want to tell you
it's a model, it's a model of the world
yes, but now, what is
really interesting is that in fact
it's not a model because when we talk
about a model of the world, there's
you finally understand anyway, I'm just speaking for myself
emotionally, about objectivity, what
I mean is that you model the world
whereas, actually, on the contrary, you
take the example of the cat, as you say
You model the world within your own
framework, with your own constraints
elasticity, physical condition
if there is a person
attached to her back finally
it's very subjective, for example
I have two hobbies.
one is sailing and the other is
making small airplanes ok
and in these two things, very windy
so, very, we shouldn't talk about Kyber
very airy, very airy
experiences that we are going to
to do at Kyber because when you sail
in any case, when I go sailing to adjust the sails
I have a kind of.
pseudo simulator
in the head of
the airflow behind the sail if
I angle it too much, there will be turbulence
behind beyond 120 degrees it doesn't work at all, just this
a little in the head is the problem
there is no need there is no need
because there is a phenomenological model
that we have in our heads, we know that it is
address the focus a little bit
a little bit more to do
attach the things behind
the big sail etc etc
we know that it's not a good idea to go completely backwards with a multihull
because we go slower than if we go a little
little and keep
the laminar flow and everything
and it's thanks to a
sort of mental model
same if I am building
a remote-controlled plane, I make a profile
her profile is a bit shady
I'm not going to run the fluid simulation
about the thing, but anyway, I know more or less
what the characteristics and everything are
but it's the same, there is a kind of
mental simulation of what is happening
the MuZero, PlaNet, Dreamer models, they are
in this idea of simulating everything in advance
with many parameters, right?
isn't that their model?
so I will get there in a
second, so all that.
it is thanks to a phenomenological model
of a very complicated phenomenon, collective
which could in principle be reduced
to a few equations
but which is very complicated
so what do the people who work at Dassault do
who make the bursts and all that
they perform the fluid flow simulation around airplanes
by what is called CFD
Computation Fluid Dynamics
it consists of saying I take a volume
I divide the volume into small cubes
and in each cube
I model the state of the air
inside it by a speed.
a density
temperature viscosity etc
and that is an abstraction because
in fact, the underlying phenomenon
is air molecules sticking
to each other and sticking
to the plane, so in fact we
forget and completely
eliminate the positions and
speeds of the air molecules
that would be too complicated to simulate anyway it wouldn't fit the reality.
we make an abstraction which are
we cut the air into small cubes
and then we solve the Navier-Stokes equations.
and this is a representation of reality which is more or less incorrect
when there are turbulence, it's not necessarily exactly correct
but that's enough, but at the end, what we want is not that, what we want
it's a lift, a drag
by the way, my planet, therefore Daniel Jerafner
I've known him for a long time, and he left
from Iman, anyway he has his box, so him
it makes a prediction in a
representation space.
but the problem, in my opinion
is not the right way
to do it, which is that it
entrains
the representation space
with an autoencoder
with a VAE actually so
you take an input frame
and auto-encode it.
you extract the information
the representation for
that your autoencoder
sticks to this step precisely
and then you use
the pre-trained encoder.
with a predictor
to create a world model.
that's the right direction but it's
not a pure JEP because it doesn't
do end-to-end training.
- Amilab so it's a
company based in France
an international company
you have offices
- it's a global global company.
since day one like
as
but then there is
a question it is
why France
why Paris
that's the question is
because you trained
the whole generation
with the FAIR Meta
you saw that in France there was what was needed and you thought that actually
there is everything needed here for it to thrive, what were the reasons
rational reasons
for setting up Amilab here?
several reasons, the first reason
is that there is a lot of talent
in Europe and in France
in particular, or talent
elsewhere in the world
who would be completely
ready to come to Paris there are worse
conditions there are worse because well
a part of the team
that worked on
all these JEPA projects
etc which are in France.
another one is in Canada
another one is in New York.
so the opening
of these three sites
Paris, New York, Montréal made sense because the team was there.
we also have a lab in Singapore
the reason for the lab in Singapore is
first, we have clients
Asian investors
we want to be able to talk to them locally
there is a lot of talent in Singapore
many come from China
but also a lot local, and then above all, with the stupid immigration policies
from the Trump administration, there are quite a few Chinese people who would like to leave China
but who can go to the United States
and Singapore, it's a good place
to get them, so there is quite a bit of talent that we can attract to Singapore.
Chinese talent
there are many
so in fact it is
a question more of talent
more than just investment or funds
then there is another big reason.
this is more geopolitical
the fact that there is
a large demand from
industry and government.
for a leading AI technology provider that is neither American nor Chinese
and therefore establish the company's headquarters in France
lifts a little of that
to tell people that we are a global company, but.
we are not American
we are not Chinese.
we are FRENCH
our investors
to be honest
about 40% of our
investors are European.
either funds or potential industrial partners or family offices
things like
that, very diverse
33% sont américains, provenant de fonds de family office, donc par exemple Jeff Bezos
and then Greycroft
which is a fund
and then and then others
family offices etc
and 27% are Asian
with a background in Dubai.
not very important, and therefore, it gives you an idea of the diversity
it's the diversification it's
everything we defend it's global
but French tech is
global, if it goes wrong we are
not Franco-French, we have
a completely global ambition.
but we rely on
French talents and on the
position of France and
Europe more generally.
as non-aligned in relation to the
American-Chinese conflict, it's called Ami Labs Ami
Friend, as for the pronunciation, it's "auto-aligned", without supervision, that's the gist.
Given what happened with
the models that are cutting themselves and all that.
You are invested in
Tapestry, you are chief
scientific officer of
Tapestry, what is it?
It's a federation of actors
for a sovereign and federated IA
among different actors
can you
say a few words
and then we finish there?
yes absolutely it's a
subject that I care about, which
is a bit orthogonal to
Ami Labs, you see?
it's Yann LeCun who said that, it
comes from him because every time
me, I have two words: incarnation and
orthogonal, except that he, when he uses
it's correct, it's not a problem
it's not a problem, we just need
now I could say, as the great Yann LeCun says, it's orthogonal
it's orthogonal, yes, it's an effort, a
little orthogonal, but not completely
which consists of
saying there are many.
many countries that would want
a kind of sovereignty
in AI
specifically for LLMs, so
it's more LLM-focused, it goes beyond that.
but for now
it's very LLM-focused.
all the countries, France, Germany
finally the European countries, India.
Vietnam, Switzerland.
The Emirates.
Korea, Japan.
Kazakhstan, all these
countries would like that.
an independent
AI
without being dependent on OpenAI,
Anthropic, Google or Meta.
or Chinese
so, for the time being, a large
part of the industry is starting to switch
to the Chinese model because they are
the best open source models
and we don't need
to use Chinese servers.
but there are still
hesitations about using
Chinese models, so the idea
is to have a federation.
of regional groups
that can be academic, NGOs.
or government
or private industry.
who would contribute to training a global model without exchanging their data.
That is, they keep sovereignty over their data.
What participants exchange are parameter vectors.
That is, a simple way to do this.
It is each region.
Each participant
has its own computing center and its own data.
in its local languages
in India there are already 300.
languages there are 22
official languages but if we
count all the local languages
and dialects
we don't end
hello the tokenizer
it would be good to
get rid of them actually
Indonesia is the same there are
300 dialects I don't know what
so it's a big
problem never.
the current actors will
train their LLM to speak
all these languages ever
they will adjust their model
to understand cultures
values systems etc.
of all the regions of the world
so these systems
cannot be aligned.
to all systems of
values, the political biases, etc.
of all the regions in the world
the only way to do that.
it's actually about providing foundational models that are open so that
everyone
can adjust them.
for their own biases.
and that's essential
because, in my opinion
everyone is talking
about the dangers of AI etc.
so there's no danger
of mass unemployment etc.
the main danger of AI
it's only a matter of time before all our
information, all the information we receive
will be provided through
AI assistants.
and if these AI assistants
come from three companies
on the US coast
or from three or four Chinese companies.
that's not good for democracy
for cultural diversity
for culture
which we have talked about many times, the
multipolarization of the world, the balances
geostrategiques et surtout aussi
si en fait ils introduisent des biais
you can't control there are
inevitably biases in every system
is biased in a particular way so
the question is, is everyone
will be biased like California, this
might be a lesser evil compared to
in some other corners
of the United States but
is it not rather a solution to have
open platforms
and that everyone can use.
fine-tune the model.
for its own biases, its own systems
you have a metamodel in the middle and you
fine-tune, you customize it in
accord with your culture, so already
there is a base model that is
trained in a distributed way, that is to say
each person has
their data, their computing center
and what they exchange
periodically, that is to say, it can be
every millisecond, every
second, or every hour
It is a vector of parameters
And the global training of
the system is not very different
from what is called
federated learning
or federative
it is that periodically each
actor receives the average parameter.
in a way
and is regularized in order to
try to get closer to this average parameter
while being trained on these
data, so it is a kind of
it's like
elastic bands, actually
you read all these parameter vectors
with elastic bands to their average
and therefore they have a
regularization that attracts them
towards the consensus model which
is the average of all these things
so they never
deviate too much
from the model, it's them
who decide to approach it
well, they have a good reason to approach it
they have a good reason to approach it
but they are not required to approach it
because at the end but they are interested
that's what's great at
the end if this thing converges
we have a model that
is a global consensus.
which is similar to if it had been
trained on all the data
without the data being
exchanged of course, so each region
preserve its sovereignty
over this data.
exchange a set of parameters
and in the end we have an open model.
accessible to everyone.
which is a kind of repository of all
human knowledge and well, listen
frankly, it's a great hope for a
global, federated AI, I think it's very cool
because in addition, it's
how it works out of interest.
and not that it means that you have
all the reasons to play the game, so here.
you see
rather than what is my favorite thing
are decentralized systems.
decentralized systems
work like this, so here.
so we organized
a workshop to start
this thing at the beginning
of May in Paris.
where we had participants
from Europe, Switzerland, the Indian Emirates.
Japanese.
and among the
Americans too, actually
companies like Nvidia
AMD, etc. they are interested
in the fact that they like
open source
and so it is enough to type on a
Project Tapestry search engine.
and you can find and participate
there is a GitHub, there is work
that has been started by IBM, so
IBM is a major participant in this.
they are very, very favorable
to open source models.
and I think it will grow, it's the
voice of the world, well listen, frankly
it's quite enthusiastic because right now
everyone is asking a lot of questions
about sovereignty, well you participate
it's a very elegant approach
you're a scientist and I have
started to talk about this idea some time ago
several years initially
internally at Facebook
and then at Meta, I don't
know how far I can go
inside Meta
unfortunately
despite the
at the time, Meta's enthusiasm for open
source hadn't really taken off
so since I left
Meta, I have
based on the mushroom
to try to get it started
and maybe the only thing we haven't
maybe said is that you are the father of the Yama
in all these models by hand
fortunately we didn't say that then
I have to say something
very easy I have never been involved
in the research
on LLM
I have nothing to do with the
LLMs that were produced
by Meta, and I did well
to speak out
because when these projects were started
I was no longer in a position of authority
I was chief scientist, which means
that people could listen to me
if they wanted, but I wasn't
their boss, so, well, listen
I have no technical contribution
to LLaMa
I encouraged them etc
LLaMa is a French product
It was started by a team
of about a dozen people in Paris
I'm sure you are all aware
do you know him
then, for LLaMa 2
it was taken up by the company so
there was a lot that happened
no, my only contribution to LLaMa was
to push for the open sourcing of LLaMa 2
listen, it was a
big one, and I remember
and I remember that it was the
CEO of HuggingFace, Clément Delangue
who had made a big thank you by saying
that it had opened an entire movement
so thank you for this movement
there you are, I know that's behind
someone is shouting at me in my ear
that we absolutely must stop
but it was a real pleasure, Yann
to have you, it was the final boss
it was the final boss for
the end of the episode, I hope
what did you do at my time
yeah yeah, it was very nice.
well, listen, it's cool, thanks for coming.
I'm glad we were able to go to it.
we're going to do 3 hours, yeah that's right.
yes, and what about you, you did 4 hours and 30 minutes.
at Lex Friedman's
- and well, listen, 7 hours
- Amilab is hiring, so that's it.
you are recruiting researchers
you are recruiting the best in the world, isn't that so?
we are recruiting researchers
we are recruiting engineers.
probably soon, at the beginning
of next year we will recruit
perhaps a different category of engineers
because we will start to collaborate
with industrial partners who could use
JPA and One Model techniques in industry.
so, we will need people
who know certain industries.
to work with their partners and
in the long term Total World Domination on will
World Model Domination was
IN FRENCH with Yann LeCun.
I hope you enjoyed it, we will
lots of annotations on
the episode it's much better
do we understand everything?
no no not everything we need to
work on it, that's it there were
some dimensions
quite high some
maths to rework
high dimensionality
thanks Yann thanks if you don't want to miss
our next episodes with guests
of the stature of Yann LeCun, other researchers, other entrepreneurs
other visionaries subscribe
to the channel À LA FRENCH like the episode
comment it to make it appear in the important ad algorithm
when the party was announced on the
French website on June 12th, less than 24 hours before
the 250 places were sold
so we had a great evening
but hundreds of people were unable to come and are on a waiting list
and we don't like frustration so
we decided to do it bigger
for the conference À LA FRENCH on December 3
we invite you
we will be 1200 people from all over France to celebrate tech IN FRENCH.
and a certain idea of tech.
We are a nation of engineers.
We invented the Minitel
before the Internet, the TGV before
Hyperloops, DivX, X264, VLC
before streaming
on Netflix. We are not going to
let anyone tell us how
we do tech, right?
Come on! The conference, which has a certain idea of technology, will be on December 3rd.
a day for the YouTube show community.
Announcements, early screenings, rare guests,
gifts, games, and attention, it's going well
Frenchmaxxer.
It's going to be the tech conference
the most incredible one you've ever seen and we're going to celebrate together
"a certain idea of technology".
You can go to alafrench.org
from now on, reserve
your seats with reduced rates
for those who don't have the means and
support prices for those who can
so we will meet on December 3
live
The interesting thing
is for the transfer because, for example, you see on Cloud Run the machines
they are limited to 6 gigabits in
fact, the bottleneck now is
loading the model, which is good for that
so we're doing Xet, and we're trying
with HuggingFace.
- Yeah, but you see, with AV1 and APV
do you have a lossless mode, depending on the model, it could be interesting.
After, I have my two guys from Trinity College working on it.
We'll talk about it in 3 weeks, they'll have at least a result before bothering you.
Basically, it's a crazy idea, so I like it.
If it works, you say "damn" and the guys
yeah, yeah, it's pointless, but essential
at the same time, who else but Mr. VLC
to do something like
that, yeah, it's the Mister
it's the game, it's the game
it's the game, it's the game.